<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Blog &#8211; djns.io</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>From Silicon to Scotch: Tech, Leadership, and Whisky</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 20:45:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Rich History and Evolution of Scotch Whisky</title>
		<link>/2024/06/the-rich-history-and-evolution-of-scotch-whisky/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[darren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 14:45:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.home.djns.io/?p=9</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Myth of Whisky’s Ancient Celtic Roots Whisky has been intertwined with Scotland&#8217;s heritage for centuries, possibly brought by Christian missionary monks. However, Highland farmers might have independently discovered distillation using their surplus barley. The enchanting tale that whisky is an ancient Celtic drink is supported by the term ‘whisky’ stemming from the Gaelic&#160;uisce beatha, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Myth of Whisky’s Ancient Celtic Roots</strong></h3>



<p>Whisky has been intertwined with Scotland&#8217;s heritage for centuries, possibly brought by Christian missionary monks. However, Highland farmers might have independently discovered distillation using their surplus barley. The enchanting tale that whisky is an ancient Celtic drink is supported by the term ‘whisky’ stemming from the Gaelic&nbsp;<em>uisce beatha</em>, meaning ‘water of life’. Despite this appealing story, spirits, including whisky, are relatively young in the timeline of alcoholic beverages.</p>



<p>Distillation techniques were refined during the Islamic Golden Age (8th to 13th centuries) and later preserved and spread by medieval monasteries across Europe. The term ‘whisky’ reflects this monastic legacy. The phrase ‘water of life’ was commonly used for distilled spirits in the Christian world, known as&nbsp;<em>aqua vitae</em>&nbsp;in Latin. This term lives on in various forms across Europe, such as&nbsp;<em>eau de vie</em>&nbsp;in France and&nbsp;<em>akvavit</em>&nbsp;in Scandinavia. Thus, modern whisky&#8217;s precursor likely emerged in Irish monasteries during the late Middle Ages.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Early References and Distilleries</strong></h3>



<p>The earliest historical mention of whisky is in the Scottish Exchequer Rolls of 1494, noting &#8220;eight bolls of malt to Friar John Cor wherewith to make aquavitae&#8221; (about 203 kilograms of malt). King James IV&#8217;s records from 1506 also indicate purchases of aquavitae, likely for drinking.</p>



<p>The Ferintosh distillery, mentioned in the Acts of the Scottish Parliament in 1690, and a reference from 1614 to distilling in a private house in Banffshire, further illustrate whisky&#8217;s early history in Scotland. By 1618, the term ‘uiskie’ appears in funeral accounts, and by 1622, local whisky is noted in a letter from Sir Duncan Campbell.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Tradition of Illicit Stills</strong></h3>



<p>Despite its relatively recent origins, whisky has a storied history of illicit distillation. Historically, ‘Parliament whisky’ was legally distilled under Crown license, while ‘poteen’ was illicitly produced. While the legal Irish whisky industry faced numerous challenges, poteen distilling thrived. By 1779, County Donegal alone had about 800 illegal stills, despite only 20 licensed distilleries in all of Ireland.</p>



<p>In the 17th century, distilling taxes in Scotland and England fostered a vibrant illicit industry, especially in the Highlands. Tales of cunning illicit distillers outsmarting excise men are integral to whisky folklore. Gavin Smith’s&nbsp;<em>The Secret Still</em>recounts colorful characters and improbable escapes, such as ‘Sarah of the Bog,’ who disguised herself as a witch to deter nosy neighbors, and Magnus Eunson, an Orkney smuggler who hid his stash in pulpits and under coffins.</p>



<p>Illicit distilling often required hidden stills, from remote sea caves to intricate setups. One account from 1824 describes a hidden still in a cavern beneath a trap door, supplied by an underground stream, with its smoke diverted through a distant cottage chimney.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Commercialisation of Whisky</strong></h3>



<p>Whisky demand soared in the mid-18th century, driven not by the scenic Highlands but by industrial Glasgow. Prof. Tom Devine suggests that northern landowners encouraged illicit distilling to increase estate profitability, while urbanisation in cities like Glasgow, where whisky provided a quicker ‘hit’ than beer, significantly fueled demand.</p>



<p>In the 1820s, Aeneas Coffey patented a new kind of still, the ‘column’ or ‘continuous’ still, producing whisky higher in alcohol and less flavorful than pot-distilled whisky but in larger quantities and at lower costs. While major Irish distilleries rejected this innovation, Scottish distilleries embraced it, leading to the rise of blended Scotch, which eventually overshadowed its Irish counterpart.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Contaminated Whisky and Legal Reforms</strong></h3>



<p>In the 19th century, urban whisky was often adulterated. Edward Burns’s&nbsp;<em>Bad Whisky</em>&nbsp;details how an 1872 investigation found that most whisky samples from Glasgow pubs were contaminated with harmful substances like turpentine and sulfuric acid. This led to health risks and antisocial behavior attributed to poorly distilled whisky.</p>



<p>A Select Committee inquiry in 1890 and subsequent Royal Commission led to legislation prohibiting the sale of whisky aged less than three years, transforming whisky into a high-quality spirit recognised worldwide.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Modern Whisky</strong></h3>



<p>Today, the whisky industry has transformed significantly. In Ireland, only four distilleries remain from the hundreds once licensed, though boutique distilleries are emerging. In the United States, micro-distilleries are joining established bourbon producers, and there’s a resurgence in rye whisky. New distilleries have opened globally, from Japan to Brazil.</p>



<p>Scotch whisky has become a symbol of refinement, even surpassing champagne in status. In 2011, Scotch whisky exports totaled £4.23 billion, marking a 62% increase over four years. The Scotch Whisky Association claims the industry contributes £125 per second to the UK economy.</p>



<p>From its origins in monastic experimentation to its modern-day status as a global luxury, whisky&#8217;s journey is rich and varied. While the days of illicit stills are mostly behind us, the spirit’s legacy and place in history remain cherished by whisky lovers worldwide.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Dual Value of Ownership</title>
		<link>/2023/08/the-dual-value-of-ownership/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[darren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 16:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=65</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We often find ourselves caught up in the allure of instant gratification. The desire for immediate rewards has gradually shifted our focus away from the deeper significance of ownership. It is important to recognise that everything we possess carries both a cost of ownership, and a cost of mastery. The Cost of Ownership The cost [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>We often find ourselves caught up in the allure of instant gratification. The desire for immediate rewards has gradually shifted our focus away from the deeper significance of ownership. It is important to recognise that everything we possess carries both a cost of ownership, and a cost of mastery.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Cost of Ownership</h2>



<p><a href="https://github.com/dazjones/dazjones.github.io#the-cost-of-ownership"></a>The cost of ownership refers to the financial investment required to acquire an item. Whether it&#8217;s a car, a piece of furniture, or a home, the price we pay is the initial entry into ownership. However, we should also consider the ongoing expenses that come with maintaining and sustaining the item. From repairs and upkeep to insurance and utilities, ownership entails a continuous financial commitment.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Value of Mastery</h2>



<p><a href="https://github.com/dazjones/dazjones.github.io#the-value-of-mastery"></a>On the other hand, the cost of mastery is the investment of time, effort, and dedication needed to truly understand and excel in using or appreciating what we own. Mastery goes beyond mere possession; it involves developing the skills, knowledge, and expertise to maximise the value and potential of an item. Whether it&#8217;s honing a craft, deepening our understanding of a subject, or mastering a skill, the pursuit of mastery enriches our experience and deepens our connection with what we own.</p>



<p>However, the current societal trend towards instant gratification has led us to prioritise the cost of ownership over the cost of mastery. With the rise of on-demand services, disposable goods, and a culture of quick fixes, the focus has shifted towards the convenience of acquiring and discarding possessions rather than investing the time and effort to truly master them. This shift has inadvertently diminished our appreciation for the long-lasting benefits that come with genuine mastery.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Finding Balance</h2>



<p><a href="https://github.com/dazjones/dazjones.github.io#finding-balance"></a>With the unconscious need for instant gratification, we risk missing out on the profound sense of fulfilment that comes from investing ourselves in the process of learning and growing. True mastery brings a level of satisfaction that transcends the initial excitement of ownership. It enables us to fully explore the potential of what we own, fostering a deeper connection and a greater sense of accomplishment.</p>



<p>So, in a society that constantly tempts us with quick fixes and immediate satisfaction, let us not forget the dual values of ownership: the cost of ownership and the cost of mastery. Let us strive to strike a balance, appreciating the importance of both aspects. By investing in our own growth and development, we can reclaim forgotten joy and rekindle our connection with the things we own.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ethical Considerations in AI: A Must for Modern Businesses</title>
		<link>/2023/06/navigating-ethical-considerations-in-the-age-of-ai/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[darren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.home.djns.io/?p=35</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As artificial intelligence (AI) continues to transform industries globally, businesses must urgently address the ethical issues that come with its adoption. AI technologies offer immense benefits in efficiency, automation, and decision-making, but they also bring complex ethical challenges that need careful handling. This post delves into the key ethical considerations for businesses today, highlighting the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"></h3>



<p>As artificial intelligence (AI) continues to transform industries globally, businesses must urgently address the ethical issues that come with its adoption. AI technologies offer immense benefits in efficiency, automation, and decision-making, but they also bring complex ethical challenges that need careful handling. This post delves into the key ethical considerations for businesses today, highlighting the importance of ethical AI practices and the need for responsible leadership.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Bias and Fairness</h4>



<p>One of the biggest ethical concerns with AI is the potential for bias and unfair outcomes. AI systems are trained on vast amounts of data, which can include historical biases and prejudices. If not addressed, these biases can perpetuate and even amplify social inequalities in areas like hiring, lending, and criminal justice.</p>



<p>Businesses need to prioritise fairness by tackling bias in AI algorithms head-on. This means regularly auditing and monitoring AI systems to spot and fix discriminatory patterns. Additionally, having diverse and inclusive teams involved in developing and testing AI models can help bring broader perspectives and minimise bias.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Privacy and Data Protection</h4>



<p>Privacy and data protection are crucial when using AI in business. AI systems rely on large volumes of data, including personal information about customers and employees. It&#8217;s essential to protect individuals&#8217; privacy and ensure their data is used responsibly.</p>



<p>Businesses must adhere to legal and ethical standards like the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) to safeguard personal data. This involves obtaining informed consent, implementing strong security measures, and adopting privacy-by-design principles. Companies should also be transparent about data management practices, giving individuals control over their data and clear information on how it&#8217;s used.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Transparency and Explainability</h4>



<p>The complex nature of some AI algorithms, like deep learning neural networks, can make transparency and explainability challenging. This lack of clarity raises accountability concerns since AI decisions can significantly impact individuals and society.</p>



<p>Businesses should aim for transparency by developing AI systems that are explainable and understandable. Using algorithms and techniques that provide clear reasons for decisions and allowing individuals to understand how their data is used can build trust among customers, employees, and stakeholders, fostering a positive view of AI adoption.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Job Displacement and Workforce Impact</h4>



<p>AI-driven automation can boost productivity and efficiency but also poses risks of job displacement and livelihood disruption for some workers.</p>



<p>Businesses need to consider the ethical implications of AI on their workforce, implementing responsible AI strategies that enhance human capabilities rather than just replacing them. Investing in reskilling and upskilling programmes can help employees adapt to AI-driven changes and ensure a fair transition for those affected by job displacement.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h4>



<p>As AI adoption rapidly evolves, businesses face numerous ethical considerations that must be addressed. By prioritising fairness, privacy, transparency, and workforce well-being, organisations can navigate the ethical challenges associated with AI. Responsible leadership and adherence to ethical AI practices will help mitigate potential risks and contribute to a more inclusive and sustainable future. Embracing ethical considerations allows businesses to harness AI&#8217;s transformative power while upholding the values and principles of a responsible and ethical business environment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
